Welcome back. So this is the last part
of Kafka architecture and if you have
already understood till now all these
edge cases and failure scenarios would
be like just uh piece of cake to be
honest if interviewer asked this you
would already know the answer for this.
So let's start without wasting any much
time. The first what happen when active
controller fails? Kindly pause the video
think about it. What happened? We have
already discussed that. So let's say
initial state is three controllers. One
controller is leader let's say active
and other two are follower which is
nothing but a standby.
So now let's say controller one got
crashed. Active controller got crashed.
Now I told you if you remember the
active controller always send its
heartbeat to the standby controller. So
they won't get any heartbeat. So what
happen is election will start raft.
Okay. So what happen is the controller
two start the election and request
votes. Controller 3 vote for controller
2. So controller 2 got two votes. Let's
say uh itself and controller 3. So it
got win
because it got two out of three
majority. Controller one already down.
That's why two out of three majority it
got. and uh controller 3 will remain
follower and now controller 2 becomes
your leader or active controller.
So impact you can say that the new
leader get elected but cluster continues
working. So there is no such big impact
happens.
Now let's say what if interview what
happen when leader partition fail. Okay
you know that right? We have already
seen that
every topic we have uh so we have a
broker broker has topic and it maintains
partition
leader and another broker have topic
same partition zero let's say it has
this follower what is leader partition
fail what happens
okay so this is the setup let's say I
have a partition zero which is replica
factor 3 So
replica factor of three means one leader
two followers.
Okay.
So what would happen? Let's say for this
partition.
Okay. So one is leader and two
followers. So one more broker
and another partition zero another
follower. Okay. So three replica. Now
what happen is broker one leader fails.
So controller who detects the failure of
this broker controller because all
broker I told you that send their
heartbeats to controller. So controller
detect the leader failure as there is no
heartbeat from the leader. Controller
trigger leader election the same thing.
Okay. So from the ISR list, ISR list
earlier was
broker one, broker two, broker 3 for
this partition zero. Broker one
considered as down, no heartbeat. So
controller out of this two in the ISR,
it will pick one. Let's say
broker two. Okay. So now they will do
internally kind of an election. If all
agree, if there is a quorum, okay, so
broker two will become a leader.
Okay.
So, controller after uh the new leader
is selected, controller updates the
metadata
that hey from leader broker one it has
become broker two and ISR is updated
that only B2 and B3 is now present.
and it will publish this information to
all the brokers.
Okay.
And for this partition zero which is
earlier leader the producer and consumer
will now connect to broker two instead
of broker one. They will connect to
broker two because this is now a leader.
So partition is just a way of
distributing the load among brokers. You
can say that.
So this case is also handled. So there
is no impact, no data loss, automatic
recovery happen, everything works fine.
Now the question is what happen when
follower partition fails. So if you
remember the ISR, we have already
discussed this use case. Let's say
partition zero three replication factor
leader follower. So currently ISR list
is let's say broker one, broker two,
broker three, this is leader let's say
this is follower this is also follower
okay three replication factor three
replicas now let's say broker three
crash the follower crashed
what would happen who will identify that
broker 3 is uh delayed or failed broker
one can also get to know so broker one
keep track of its follower. You can say
that fetch request
because brokers are keep on fetch
followers are keep on fetching from the
leader to keep themselves up to date. So
now let's say if broker 3 is down there
is no fetch request from this broker 3
to the leader. So this leader get to
know that yes there is something wrong
with the B3. So what it will do is it
will update the ISR. it will remove B3
and it will up pass it to the controller
and controller will update the metadata.
Okay, so that's what I have mentioned
here. So leader detect broker 3 is
unresponsive. No timely fetch call
controller removes the B3 from the ISR.
Generally here if you see that the
broker
this leader broker removes from the ISR
and pass this remove request to the
controller. Ultimately controller update
its cluster metadata. You can say that.
And here if you see that uh system
continues normally
no issues producer will still be able to
write. Okay. Now in the ISR only this
two are present into the three. So no
issues and when B3 recovers it will
again get back added to the ISR. Let's
say B3 got recovered
and uh
what happened is that controller again
added
and it start sending the fetch calls
then it will again get added to the ISR
okay so it's depend upon the broker 3
recovery once it get recovered and it
does a catch up with the leader okay
leader will identify that yes it is
fetching the data now and it has already
done the catch up. It will get added
back to this ISR and it will pass it to
the controller. Controller update the
metadata.
What happen when topic fails? This is
tricky question because topic can never
fail. I told you that topic is just a
category or folder. So if something fail
partition fails not topic like we have
already seen above what happened that
leader partition fail. What happen when
follower partition fail? So topic never
fails.
What happen when consumer fail? We have
also discussed this part. Okay. So if
any consumer fails
scenario one I'm showing you consumer
crash before committing offset. Okay. So
now let's say that consumer pull the
event from 100 to 199.
Okay.
Consumer start processing event 100 to
150. So it reached till 150 it is
processing and it crashed at this point
of time and it restart come back again.
So what it will do is it will ask the
group coordinator
when I say that it ask Kafka it means
Kafka server which is the broker and in
case of consumer we call them group
coordinator because call goes to one of
the broker only for a particular group
uh consumer group. What's my last
offset? The last offset would return
that still like 99. You have to start
from 100. So it has to reprocess this
again. 100 101. So this is one failure
scenario.
So another scenario is consumer
heartbeat timeout. So consumer doesn't
fail but use case is that long
processing time or you can say that if
consumer fails also its heartbeat got
missed. So what is the uh steps consumer
poll events consumer start processing.
Now let's say that it took 6 minutes.
Okay. And it is still processing and we
have set this into the configuration.
Max pole interval is 5 minutes. What
does it mean? Just say that the group
coordinator after 5 minutes should get
one heartbeat from the consumer. In
simple term is this. Now since consumer
is already busy with processing from
last 6 minute, it forgot to send the
heartbeat to the group coordinator.
Okay. So what group coordinator will see
that this consumer is dead
and it will
assign what it will do is it will
reassign this partition to some other
consumer
and now what would happen is original
consumer finished processing and it will
try to commit but group coordinator will
reject it. So understand this use case
that you have a consumer one you have a
consumer two consumer one is reading
from let's say
order events partition zero
okay so this is in broker one and broker
three is there let's say group
coordinator
from previous video you already know
that what group coordinator in case of
consumer is that it's part of let's say
group consumer group notification.
So for this group notification
okay all the offset related information
all the consumer
uh metadata information is present by
this broker only
okay because of hash this group
notification group ID mod 50 it will
always return let's say the partition
let's say 23 or something any partition
and this group holds that partition as a
leader
So always for this group the call goes
to one of the broker that's why that
group is known as group coordinator.
Okay.
So here what happen is
this group coordinator is waiting for
all the consumer which is currently it
is maintaining for this group. Let's say
consumer one, consumer two, consumer 3.
Consumer one is handling let's say
partition zero of order events.
Okay, this is managing partition one of
order events. Now till 5 minutes there
is no heartbeat from this consumer. What
it will this group coordination assume
that this consumer one is dead. So what
it will do is it will assign this
partition zero to some other consumer
order even and it will remove from the
group for now.
But let's say if once it process and
then it say that hey commit this offset
that hey for
notification group order event top a
partition zero I have pro processed till
100 and it will try to write update this
consumer offset.
It will not enterain this group
coordinator will not enterain because
this consumer one is been currently
removed from the group. So it has to add
itself again
and then this group coordinator will
assign some other topic to it.
Okay. But till now this consumer 3 which
has been reassigned it will again from
the consumer offset take out that okay
for this partition zero of this order
event top a what was the last offset and
it will start processing again from that
one.
Okay.
Now another thing is what happen when
broker fails
this also we have already discussed okay
let's say you have three brokers
six partitions and replication factor is
three
this is just a setup now let's say
broker one got failed
who will detect the failure
controller because all the brokers send
the heartbeat to active controller.
Okay. Now what would happen is what
controller will do for each partition
where broker one was leader a new leader
is elected from ISR. We have already
discussed that and it will update the
metadata.
Okay. And also for each partition where
broker one was follower it will remove
from the ISR. So generally ISR is
updated
from this ISR list. Let's say broker
one, broker two, broker 3. If broker one
is crashed, out of this one of the
leader is selected.
Okay.
And wherever the broker one was follower
from that it was removed. Let's say
broker one was for partition two it was
a follower. So for partition two ISR
list it would have broker one, broker
two, broker three. This is leader, this
is follower, this is follower. Since
broker one is down from this it would
get removed.
So this metadata update will happen and
will pass it to all the brokers. So
system continues manually. No data loss
automatic recovery will happen if any
broker goes down.
Okay. So all this we have already
discussed while we were covering uh
subtopics of Kafka. It's just like I
just want to accumulate all this kind of
interview questions which failure
scenario which interviewer put in the
most of the scenarios.
So with that we have completed the Kafka
architecture.
Now what next I will do is we will try
to now implement it. Now if you
understand this Kafka architecture fully
the implementation part like using it
using the Kafka would be very very easy.
Okay, it's just like connecting the
dots. That's solve. We already know that
okay
what is broker, what is topic, what is
partition cluster where we can even if
you know this fully you can even check
the locks also the segments index. Okay.
So things will become pretty clear when
you work with Kafka if you understand uh
the whole whatever we have discussed in
the architecture videos of the Kafka.
Okay guys hope uh this is helpful and if
you have any doubt let me know we can
discuss further. Bye.